<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Projects | Daniel Sonnenstuhl</title><link>https://sonnenstuhl.github.io/project/</link><atom:link href="https://sonnenstuhl.github.io/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Projects</description><generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 01 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://sonnenstuhl.github.io/media/icon_hu13d247283255ebcf9731518c742cb48e_5056_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url><title>Projects</title><link>https://sonnenstuhl.github.io/project/</link></image><item><title>(Self-)Employment and Weak Institutions</title><link>https://sonnenstuhl.github.io/project/self/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sonnenstuhl.github.io/project/self/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="abstract">Abstract&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Many low-income countries suffer from limited contract enforcement and an ensuing low-trust environment. This can create labor market frictions by establishing mistrust
between employers and employees. While consequences for firms have been well established, this paper illuminates the consequences for the labor supply side. Drawing
on original data from Nigeria, this paper shows that workers are concerned about an employer not honoring the work agreement and paying wage as agreed. This concern directly
affects peoples&amp;rsquo; preferences and seems to make self-employment more attractive. Quantifying the degree of uncertainty with a choice experiment, this paper finds that
workers value a very high degree of certainty about correct wage payment equivalent to a 16.8% salary increase. Hence, this paper suggests that the inherently uncertain
environment of low-income countries can have direct implications for workers and their choices when seeking employment.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Religion, Health, and Behavior: Evidence from Nigeria</title><link>https://sonnenstuhl.github.io/project/rel_health_behav/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sonnenstuhl.github.io/project/rel_health_behav/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="abstract">Abstract&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Religion has influenced human lives for centuries. But despite its undeniable importance, we still lack systematic evidence on the implications of people’s real-life interactions with religious institutions. How does joining a church affect individuals’ lives? What are the specific impacts of different religious motifs? And what motivates individuals to join a church in the first place? Through a unique partnership with one of the largest Nigerian Pentecostal denominations we will address these questions and provide causal evidence on the impacts of religious engagement using the context of African Pentecostalism, one of the most remarkable phenomena of religious dynamism.
We will examine four distinct aspects of people’s interactions with Pentecostal churches. First, the salience of different religious motifs in the denomination’s proselytization activities allow us to identify the motivations underlying people’s decision to join a Pentecostal church. Second, the denomination’s proselytization activities rely on randomly approaching pedestrians at public locations. This creates a quasi-experimental research design allowing us to apply an instrumental variable strategy, instrumenting the decision to join the Pentecostal denomination with contact from the LFW proselytization team. Third, we will disentangle the effect of joining a Pentecostal denomination into different channels using a pre-registered randomized controlled trial (RCT). We will use the denomination’s practice to integrate new church members into the community by offering study groups. Fourth, we will develop an extension of the club good model to account for the observed empirical patterns of religious dynamics in urban Nigeria.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>